It's two people.
有兩個人
Is it the same duo we've been after?
是我們一直在追捕的那兩人嗎?
The footprints look similar.
腳印很相似
Jeez, why does this happen when the master is out?
要命,為什麼剛好發生在 主人不在家的時候?
What's the damage?
有什麼損失?
One bag of wheat flour and dried meat.
一袋麵粉和肉乾
It's no good, Boss.
狀況不妙,老大
Their footprints are mixed with other footprints so we can't track them.
他們的腳印跟其他腳印 混在一起了,我們無法追蹤
Oh well...
算了
They don't take much,
他們偷得不多
but this is becoming a bad habit.
他們已經養成壞習慣了
Do they think we don't notice or something?
他們難道以為我們不會發現嗎?
We have no choice but to teach them a lesson, I guess.
我想...我們也只好給他們一個教訓了
That's amazing!
太神奇了
The old master must be very fond of you.
老主人一定很喜歡你
- You think so? - Of course.
-妳這麼認為嗎? -當然囉
He lends you horses and equipment
他把馬匹和設備借給你
and even lets you eat at the same table.
甚至邀你同桌吃飯
Yeah, but that's just our reward for doing his chores.
對啦,但那只是獎勵我們 幫他做了家務
We're slaves, remember?
我們是奴隸,記得吧?
Normally, we don't get any reward.
我們通常不會得到任何獎賞
I see...
是喔...
Now that you mention it, that's true.
現在聽妳這麼說,的確是這樣
You see?
對吧?
But... why would he be fond of me?
但是,他為什麼會喜歡我?
- Um... - Sorry...
-嗯... -抱歉
It's because you are a good man. But it seems you aren't aware of that.
那是因為你是個好人 但你似乎還不知道這一點
What...?
什麼?
What? No, well... Oh, please...
什麼?沒有啦...呃...或許吧
Einar.
埃納爾
- See you later. - I'm nothing like that...
-等等見囉 -我才沒有...
Huh? Oh...
咦?這...
Is he trying to be nice?
他在對我示好嗎?
He's also a good guy. Even though he's quiet.
他也是個好人,雖然他很沉默
Yes.
對呀
Arnheid!
阿奴納
Oh no, it's the mistress.
唉呀,是女主人
- Sorry for taking your time. - No, don't be.
-抱歉,擔誤了妳的時間 -不,別這麼說
Now that I have someone to talk to,
現在我有了聊天的對象
I have something to look forward to every morning.
我每天早上都很期待這件事呢
See you.
再見
Yes, see you tomorrow morning.
好,明天早上見囉
She called me a "good man."
她說我是個好人
I'm a good man!
我是個好人
You're out here fooling around while breakfast isn't even ready?
只會在外面鬼混 竟然連早餐都還沒準備好?
Must be nice to be you.
妳過得挺愜意的嘛
I'm sorry, ma'am.
對不起,夫人
We didn't buy you just for fun.
我們買下妳不是買好玩的
Earn your keep.
給我好好做事
Yes, ma'am.
是的,夫人
My husband will return from the town meeting today.
我先生今天結束 鎮民大會之後就會回家
He may come home with guests,
可能會帶一些客人回來
so be prepared for that.
做好心理準備
Well, I guess
也是啦,我想
a slave boy is a good match for a slave girl.
男奴隸跟女奴隸的確很相配
Oh, they've sprouted! These are wheat sprouts, Thorfinn.
哇,發芽了,這些是小麥芽,托爾芬
They look...
它們看起來...
so frail.
好脆弱
Is this normal?
這樣是正常的嗎?
Yeah, it's normal.
對,很正常
How intriguing. This turns into bread, huh?
不可思議,這會變成麵包?
- Are you in awe? - Yeah.
-你很驚訝嗎? -對
It's moving, isn't it?
它在動,是吧?
Yeah, it's amazing.
對呀,太神奇了
We'll grow them and sell them, and grow them and sell them,
我們要不停地種小麥、賣小麥
and buy back our freedom.
贖回我們的自由
No matter how many years it will take...
不管需要多少年的時間
All right! I'm fired up now!
好的,我燃起了熊心壯志
This is our first step toward freedom!
這是我們邁向自由的第一步
We'll clear this forest
我們要再清出更多空地
and plant twice as much next year.
讓明年的栽種量加倍
Hey,
是說...
we have the chance to become free as long as we cultivate this field,
只要我們在這片土地上耕種 就有機會贖回自由
but I wonder what will happen to Arnheid?
但不知阿奴納的未來會怎樣?
I don't know. Why don't you ask her?
我不知道,你何不去問她?
Is it okay to ask about that kind of stuff?
問她這種問題好嗎?
More importantly, what are we going to do with this today?
更重要的是,我們今天 要怎麼處理它們?
Huh? Oh, the wheat? There's nothing to do for a while.
什麼?小麥芽嗎? 有好一陣子什麼事都不用做
I see. Then let's start cutting trees again--
了解,那我們再繼續砍樹吧
- And so, we'll pray. - Huh? Pray?
-但是,我們要祈禱 -什麼?祈禱?
Oh, my God!
上帝啊!
Let it grow! Let it produce!
讓它長大,讓它結穗
Expel bugs and mold!
趕走所有的害蟲和黴菌
Make it rain!
下雨吧!
- Now, together. - Huh?
-過來,一起祈禱 -什麼?
Pray... to what?
向誰祈禱?
Anything is fine. Be it Yahweh or Freyja.
向誰都可以,雅威或是芙雷雅都可以
We need all the help we can get.
我們得想盡辦法求助
Just sit down.
坐下來
Whether it's a good or bad harvest is, for the most part, out of our control.
收成是好是壞 大部分都超出我們的控制範圍
We have no offerings to make. So we have to put our hearts into it.
我們無法提供任何供品 只能獻上我們虔敬的心
Let it grow!
讓它長大吧
Come on, put your hands together and join me.
快點,雙手合十,加入我
Let it... grow...
讓它長大
- I can't hear you! - Sorry!
-我聽不到 -抱歉
- Let it grow! - Don't be embarrassed.
-讓它長大 -別害羞
It's more embarrassing when you hesitate!
你猶豫不決反而更丟臉
- Y... Yes! - Ready...
-好... -準備...
Expel bugs and mold! Make it rain!
趕走所有的害蟲和黴菌,下雨吧
This farm hasn't changed at all.
這座農場還是老樣子
Are Mom and Olmar doing well, Dad?
媽跟歐瑪還好嗎,爸?
Yeah, Olmar is doing too well that I have my hands full.
很好,歐瑪的表現好到 讓我忙到不可開交
He's itching to go to battle like you.
他急著跟你一樣上戰場
I see he hasn't changed since he was a little kid. Too bad he's such a chicken.
看來他從小到大都沒變過 可惜他是個膽小鬼
Everyone has their own strengths and weaknesses, Thorgil.
每個人都各有其優缺點,托爾吉爾
He isn't cut out for battle. It is best
他不是打仗的料,做人
for people to stay where they're meant to be.
最重要的是要有自知之明
Well, you never know.
這個嘛,世事難料
Sometimes the battlefield can change a man, just like King Canute.
戰場有時候能夠改變一個人 就如同庫奴特國王
"King"?
國王?
Nobody calls him prince anymore.
再也沒人叫他王子了
He has changed a lot with this war.
戰爭讓他變了一個人
He now leads the army with confidence.
他現在能夠自信滿滿地帶兵作戰
Why don't you try sending Olmar to the battlefield?
你何不試著把歐瑪送上戰場?
Don't be ridiculous.
別開玩笑了
He can't fight with his level of skill.
憑他那點雕蟲小技,如何上戰場?
Oh, it's the master.
是主人
Oh, perfect timing.
正是時候
Is that...
那是...
Just as I thought, it's Thorgil!
就跟我想得一樣,是托爾吉爾
- When did you get back? - Five or six days ago.
-你什麼時候回來的? -五、六天前
I met my dad at the town meeting
我在鎮民大會上碰到我爸
so I decided to visit.
所以決定回家看看
You're one tenacious man. How are you still alive?
你的命還真硬,竟然還活著?
It's because you trained me, Snake.
多虧了你的訓練,蛇
Snake, what are you pulling?
蛇,你拉的是什麼?
Oh, that's right. Hey!
喔,對了,喂
Come on, hurry up!
過來,快點
They're thieves. I was going to hand them over to you.
他們是小偷,我正打算把他們交給你
Thieves?
小偷?
There have been multiple cases of theft that use the same tactics.
有好幾起竊案,都是同樣的手法
My gut tells me they were all done by them.
我的直覺告訴我,是他們兩個幹的
Whether they're kids or not, theft is still theft.
不管他們是否只是個孩子 偷竊就是不對的
Please give them a punishment, Master.
請懲罰他們,主人
Brother, my hands hurt.
哥,我的手好痛
What'll happen to us?
我們會有什麼樣的下場?
Are we going to die?
我們會死嗎?
Don't worry.
別擔心
It's okay.
沒事的
I am with you.
有我在
In the end,
到頭來
they call us an army,
他們把我們看成是一個軍隊
but no one cares if you're an ally or not.
但沒人在乎你是敵是友
Once the battle starts,
戰爭一旦開打
each tribe attacks the target on their own agenda.
每個部隊在攻擊的時候 其實都各懷鬼胎
As if to say, "I'm the most daring man of the North Sea!"
彷彿都在對眾人宣稱 ”我才是北海最勇敢的人”
After the battle, there's a fun pillaging competition.
戰役結束後,再藉由掠奪競賽找樂子
It's common to see people
他們經常為了爭奪女奴人選
fighting over women they can sell.
打得不可開交
- Olmar. - Huh?
-歐瑪 -怎麼了?
How about it? Do you want to go to England?
這樣如何?你想去英格蘭嗎?
What? You don't want to?
什麼?你不想去?
Of... Of course, I'll go to battle.
當然囉,我想上戰場
I'm ready to show my skills.
我已經準備好展現我的能耐了
That's my younger brother!
這才是我的好弟弟
Maybe I'll give you a souvenir then.
或許我該給你一個紀念品
- Hey, bring that necklace. - Yes.
-嘿,把那條項鍊拿來 -是
What is this? Dried meat? Can I eat it?
這是什麼?肉乾?我可以吃嗎?
You can if you want, but ears aren't that tasty.
想要的話就拿去吃吧 但耳朵不太好吃
Huh?
什麼?
The ears of Englishmen.
英格蘭人的耳朵
Ears?
耳朵?
- Uh... - You're such a chicken!
-這個... -你真的很膽小
How are you going to get by like that?
你這種德性要怎麼活下去?
We are sons of the Iron Fist Ketil.
我們可是鐵拳凱特爾的兒子啊
Iron Fist?
鐵拳?
You don't know? Our dad was legendary as a youth.
你不知道?我們的老爸 年輕的時候可是個傳奇人物
The moment he starts fighting, his weapon becomes destroyed
他一旦開始作戰 他的武器立刻就毀了
because of his brute strength.
因為他力大無窮
So from that point on he fights using his bare fists.
所以,自此以後 他便赤手空拳上戰場
And despite that, he still kills the most enemies.
儘管手無寸鐵 殺敵數量沒人贏得了他
What? Our dad?
什麼?我們的老爸?
When you talk to the older warriors, they mention the "Iron Fist" a lot.
當你跟老一輩的戰士聊天時 他們很常提到鐵拳這號人物
Show more respect to Dad.
對老爸尊敬一點吧
You must be tired from your trip, Thorgil.
長途跋涉 你一定累了吧,托爾吉爾?
Get some rest inside.
快進去休息吧
- I'm not that weak. - Thorgil...
-我身體沒那麼虛 -托爾吉爾
Fine, Iron Fist Ketil.
好啦,鐵拳凱特爾
- Master... - What?
-主人 -怎麼了?
Pardon me, but can you
冒犯了,但可否請你
take care of that before you go and rest?
在休息之前,先把這件事處理完?
First, why don't you tell me your names.
首先,告訴我你們的名字
Hey! Say your name!
喂,快說出你們的名字
Stop that! They can't speak because they're scared.
別這樣,他們說不出話 是因為太害怕了
I'm sorry.
我很抱歉
Now, tell me your names.
告訴我你們的名字吧
Sture...
舒爾
My sister's name is Thora.
我妹妹叫朵拉
I see.
了解
Sture and Thora, huh?
舒爾和朵拉?
Is there anyone who can speak in your defense?
有人能夠幫你們說說好話嗎?
Their family includes a mother and a baby.
他們家還有他們的母親和一個嬰兒
Their mother was sick in bed so we didn't bring her.
他們的母親臥病在床 所以我們沒有把她帶過來
We don't know where their father is.
我們不知道他們的父親在哪裡
What's your father's name? Is he all right?
你們的父親叫什麼名字?他還好嗎?
Answer him.
快回答
Our dad is named Snorri.
我們的父親叫史諾第
He went out to sell vegetables last fall...
他去年秋天出門賣菜...
and hasn't come back since.
就再也沒回來過了
Is your grandfather's name Bo, perchance?
難道你外公的名字是波?
Yes!
對
It's Snorri, son of Bo.
是波的兒子史諾第
He is in debt and owes you ground rent, Master.
他負債累累,還欠你地租
Oh, that Snorri!
噢,那個史諾第喔
I was wondering why he hasn't shown up lately.
我還覺得奇怪最近怎麼都沒看到他
He's dead for sure.
他肯定是死了
It's been a whole year. He won't be coming back.
已經一年了,他不會回來了
Some bandits probably killed--
可能被土匪殺了...
No! Dad is just gone for a little bit!
不可能,我爸只是出門一下子而已
Families who lose their breadwinner
失去經濟支柱的家庭
are customarily taken in by other families as workers.
通常會成為其他家庭的傭人
These children may have a chance,
這些孩子或許有機會
but they come with a sick mother and her infant.
但他們家還有生病的母親和嬰兒
Nobody will want to take them in.
沒有家庭會願意收留他們
What is the matter?
怎麼了嗎,老公?
I got something in my eye.
有東西跑進我的眼睛裡了
So, what did these two steal?
這兩個人偷了什麼?
They have a slew of other offenses but for now,
他們還做了很多不應該的事,但目前
they confessed to stealing one bag of wheat flour.
他們承認偷了一袋麵粉
My subordinate and I are witnesses to that.
我的部下和我是目擊證人
You better not have threatened them to speak.
你們最好沒有脅迫他們召供
I wouldn't do such a thing!
我才不屑這麼做
I did lay a trap, though.
但我確實設下了陷阱
Until this bag becomes empty... That's how much time I'll give you.
在麵粉流光之前 我就給你這麼多的時間
If you own up to it, I'll go easy on you.
如果你承認的話,我就不會太為難你
Our bags have our master's name inscribed on the bottom.
袋子底部刻有我們主人的名字
That's the same thing as threatening!
這跟脅迫有什麼兩樣?
Huh? No, it's not.
是嗎?不是,這才不是
If he was innocent, there would be no reason to confess.
如果他是無辜的,他就沒必要招認
Then that settles it. It'll cost one arm.
那麼,這就解決了 他們得拿一條手臂來償還
My little sister is still small. Have mercy on her!
我妹妹年紀還小,請放過她吧
Then take on your sister's share of the punishment.
那你就連你妹妹的份一起罰
We'll cut off both arms.
我們會砍下你的雙臂
No... Brother...
不要啊,哥哥...
Well...
是說...
I don't want to go back on my word. Can you go easy on them?
我不想說話不算話 可以請你別太為難他們嗎?
Well, I think we've come to a conclusion, Dad.
這個嘛,我認為就該這麼辦,爸
How terrifying... It's hard to believe he is my son.
太可怕了,真不敢相信他是我兒子
Why did you have to steal from my farm?
你們為什麼要到我的農場偷東西?
I have no choice but to punish you two.
我別無選擇,只能懲罰你們
I must object. That is the same as giving them a death sentence.
我反對,這無疑是判了他們兩個死刑
- It is a punishment too severe for theft. - Pater...
-對於小偷來說,這種懲罰太過了 -帕特...
May I have permission to give my opinion, Master?
主人,可以允許我發表意見嗎?
Oh! Yes!
噢,可以
Go ahead, Pater.
請說吧,帕特
As someone who takes care of the finances of this farm,
這座農場的財務由我管理
I cannot agree with imposing a severe punishment on the young boy.
我無法同意把這麼重的懲罰 強加在這個小男孩身上
If you cut off both of his arms, we cannot use him for anything.
如果你砍下他的雙臂 他對我們來說就毫無用處了
Sture, how old are you?
舒爾,你幾歲?
Twelve.
12歲
Perfect. That is the age when children can start working like adults.
太好了,孩子從這個年紀開始 就可以像大人一樣工作了
The amount he stole and his father's debt must be collected.
他偷走的東西 和他父親的債務一定得償還
Let us have them work and pay that off.
就讓他們替我們工作還債
I suggest that we hire them and their mother
我提議我們僱用他們和他們的母親
to work as farmhands on this farm.
來農場工作,做農場幫手
As for their jobs, they can work as farmhands and cultivate
至於工作內容 他們可以做幫手的工作和種田
the land which you've already leased to them.
您已經把田地租給他們了
I will provide technical training to Sture.
我會提供技術訓練給舒爾
If we raise him to be a proficient worker,
如果我們將他培養成熟練的工人
he will be able to compensate for these damages.
他就能夠彌補那些損失
And there will be no need for him to steal anymore.
他就再也沒有必要偷東西了
It will solve the root of the problem.
這才能從根本解決問題
Absolutely! We need compensation for the damages. So--
沒錯,我們得彌補損失,那麼...
With all of that in mind,
考慮到這一點的話
I believe flogging would suffice as punishment.
我認為用杖刑做為懲罰已綽綽有餘
- Huh? - Well, I understand the logic behind it.
-什麼? -嗯,我理解你的邏輯
Uh... Well...
那麼...
Well, they're going to work and pay back what they stole.
他們可以用工作 來賠償他們偷走的東西
Their punishment will be in the form of a debt.
他們的懲罰就用債務取代就夠了
We can't just let them go without any form of
主人,我們不能就這樣放過他們
corporal punishment, Master.
一定要有體罰才行
We have to draw the line, or else we won't be taken seriously.
我們必須要有原則 否則他們不會把我們說的話當真
Plus, nobody wants to be around people with a habit of stealing.
況且,沒有人想要與小偷為伍
You'll be doing them a favor by disciplining them.
您教訓他們,反而對他們有益
So, how many times will it be?
那麼,我們該打幾下?
Five...
五下...
Ten... Ten times.
十...十下好了
Ten times each?
每個人十下?
We'll start with you, boy. Clench your teeth.
小男孩,先從你開始,咬緊牙關
- Brother... - Stand back!
-哥哥... -退後
- Brother! - Twenty times!
-哥哥 - 20下
Hit me 20 times, please!
拜託打我20下
So have mercy on my little sister!
請饒了我的妹妹
Interesting! He sure has guts.
有意思,他的確有膽識
Dad, please let me do it.
爸,請讓我來動手
What? But you don't know how to hold back.
什麼?但你不懂得手下留情
- Don't kill him, okay? - Yes.
-別把他殺了,好嗎? -好
- Make it light.
-輕一點
- Don't hit his head. - Okay.
-別打到他的頭 -好啦...
Lightly, right? Here we go, kid.
輕一點,是嗎?來囉,孩子
Brother!
哥哥
- One! - Wait!
-一 -等等
Stop it, Thorgil. I will do it.
住手,托爾吉爾,讓我來
Where's Dad?
爸爸他人呢?
- It seems he went to bed. - My, my...
-似乎是上床睡覺了 -我的天...
Iron Fist Ketil is up in years, I guess.
看樣子,這些年下來 鐵拳凱特爾也老了
It's a lie. The whole Iron Fist story...
什麼鐵拳的故事,全都是謊言
Nordic men can't survive if they're wimps.
懦弱的北方人是活不下去的
Everyone expects
每個人都期望我
me to be brave, as if it's a given.
勇敢無畏,似乎我生來就是如此
No one would ever believe
沒有人會相信...
that a prominent figure like myself would tell such a lie.
像我這樣一個大人物 竟然會說出這麼大的謊言
I'm terrified...
我很怕...
of my son Thorgil.
我的兒子托爾吉爾
of war and violence.
戰爭和暴力
There should be nothing wrong with being kind.
慈悲為懷並沒有錯
I understand your pain.
我明白你的痛苦
You are the only one
妳是唯一一個
who says that to me. You are the only one...
對我說這種話的人,妳是唯一一個...
whom I can be completely honest with.
我能夠坦誠相對的人
Stay by my side.
留在我身邊
Without you,
沒有妳
this world
這個世界...
is all darkness.
只剩下一片黑暗
"An Empty Man."
空虛的人
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻譯:歐德慧